<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rotaract | Dr. Ambrogi</title>
    <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/category/rotaract/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/category/rotaract/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Rotaract</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/media/icon_hu6f17802a8753f91cf448893ebab15783_26243_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Rotaract</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/category/rotaract/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>My journey in Rotaract</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/ag_rotaract/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/ag_rotaract/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My journey in Rotaract in Canada begun on April 2021 when I joined the Rotaract Club of Kingston as a regular member. Soon after, it became very clear to me that I wanted to be more involved in the community and help in anyway I could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On July 2022 I became the President of the Kingston Rotaract Club. Covid-19 had a very bad impact on our Club, which at that time had only 4 active members. I decided the focus of my year to be &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;giving help to all new comers to Kingston&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; with a particular enphasis on families coming from countries with geopolitical issues, or refugees from Syria and Ukraine. I started a fruitful collaboration with the Newcomer center at KEYS in Kingston, and we organized several fundraisers and events to support newcomers and refugess in our community (for more details check our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rotaractclubofkingston.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;). All these activities generated interest in many youg professionals and graduate students and our Club went from 4 active members to more than 10. On a District level, I became part of the committee in charge of organizing the Rotary District Conference for 2024 during DG Pardeep year (check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rotary7040.com/sitepage/discon-2024&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DisCon24&lt;/a&gt; website).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of July 2023 I was appointed Assistant Governor Rotaract and I will have the priviledge to work with the district leadership to ensure Rotaract and Rotaractors thrive in our District. I look very much forward to this new amazing opportunity, and I hope many other young professionals will get interested in the beautiful word of Rotaract.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
