<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academic | FA</title>
    <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/tag/academic/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/tag/academic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Academic</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Academic</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/tag/academic/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was awarded the 2024 Silver Wrench Award by the MME Department.</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/swa_award_24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/swa_award_24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Winter term 2024 I had the pleasure, AGAIN, to teach Fluid Mechanics to second year Queen&amp;rsquo;s Engineering students. It has been, once again, an amazing experience insightful and fullfilling. During the Mechanical Engineering Banquet I received for the second consecutive year the Silver Wrench Award!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented on an annual basis, this award recognizes the professor who displays the most interest and enthusiasm towards Mechanical Engineering as chosen by the graduating year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to extend my profound gratitude to my wife Veronica, who has the courage to stand by my side every single day, to everyone in the Department, including my supervisor &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Piomelli&lt;/a&gt; and my fellow colleagues at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/TSMLab.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TSM-Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and to every instructor I have had the pleasure to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I successfully defended my PhD thesis</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/defense-success/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/defense-success/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a fantastic journey!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 8th, 2023 I successfully defended my PhD thesis titled &amp;ldquo;Characterization of unsteady separation on a turbulent boundary layer&amp;rdquo;. I had a beautiful discussion with the examination committee and gained a lot of useful insights. I now cannot wait to jump into the next step of my academic career! Stay tuned &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These 4 years at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University have been the best of my life. I met incredible people, bright minds, and excited students ready to start their own journey. I had the opportunity to travel to conferences, publish papers, give seminars, and teach core courses in mechanical engineering. It&amp;rsquo;s a path that I strongly suggest to anyone with a deep curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge thank you goes to my supervisor, &lt;a href=&#34;https://smithengineering.queensu.ca/directory/faculty/ugo-piomelli&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Piomelli&lt;/a&gt;, to my colleagues at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://smithengineering.queensu.ca/mme/faculty/piomelli/tsm-lab.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TSM Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and to the wonderful admin &amp;amp; academic staff of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://smithengineering.queensu.ca/mme/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mechanical and Materials Engineering Department&lt;/a&gt; in the Stephen J. R. Smith Faculty of Engineering and Applied Science at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University. You have been part of my journey and I will cherish every single memory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My journey in Rotaract</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/ag_rotaract/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/ag_rotaract/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My journey in Rotaract in Canada begun on April 2021 when I joined the Rotaract Club of Kingston as a regular member. Soon after, it became very clear to me that I wanted to be more involved in the community and help in anyway I could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On July 2022 I became the President of the Kingston Rotaract Club. Covid-19 had a very bad impact on our Club, which at that time had only 4 active members. I decided the focus of my year to be &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;giving help to all new comers to Kingston&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; with a particular enphasis on families coming from countries with geopolitical issues, or refugees from Syria and Ukraine. I started a fruitful collaboration with the Newcomer center at KEYS in Kingston, and we organized several fundraisers and events to support newcomers and refugess in our community (for more details check our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rotaractclubofkingston.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;). All these activities generated interest in many youg professionals and graduate students and our Club went from 4 active members to more than 10. On a District level, I became part of the committee in charge of organizing the Rotary District Conference for 2024 during DG Pardeep year (check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rotary7040.com/sitepage/discon-2024&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DisCon24&lt;/a&gt; website).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of July 2023 I was appointed Assistant Governor Rotaract and I will have the priviledge to work with the district leadership to ensure Rotaract and Rotaractors thrive in our District. I look very much forward to this new amazing opportunity, and I hope many other young professionals will get interested in the beautiful word of Rotaract.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was awarded the 2023 Silver Wrench Award by the MME Department.</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/swa_award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/swa_award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Winter term 2023, I had the wonderful opportunity to teach Fluid Mechanics I (MECH241) to second year engineering students at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University. It was an amazing experience: it was refreshing, stimulating, and exciting. It was my very first time desiging a course from the beginning, and teaching some of the topic I am extremely passionate about. For my work as teaching fellow, I received the Silver Wrench Award on April 2023 during the Mechanical Engineering Banquet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented on an annual basis, this award recognizes the professor who displays the most interest and enthusiasm towards Mechanical Engineering as chosen by the graduating year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to extend my profound gratitude to my wife Veronica, who has the courage to stand by my side every single day, to everyone in the Department, including my supervisor &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Piomelli&lt;/a&gt; and my fellow colleagues at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/TSMLab.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TSM-Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and to every instructor I have had the pleasure to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was awarded the 2022 Bronze Wrench Award by the MME Department.</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/bwa_award/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/bwa_award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented on an annual basis, this award recognizes a teaching assistant of Mechanical Engineering for their contribution to the undergraduate class as voted by all years (2nd , 3rd and 4th ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to extend my profound gratitude to my wife Veronica, who has the courage to stand by my side every single day, to everyone in the Department, including my supervisor &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Piomelli&lt;/a&gt; and my fellow colleagues at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/TSMLab.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TSM-Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and to every instructor I have had the pleasure to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was awarded the 2022 Dean&#39;s Teaching Assistant Award.</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/dta_award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/dta_award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means EVERYTHING to me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been selected as a recipient of the 2022 Dean&amp;rsquo;s Teaching Assistant (DTA) award by the Department of Mechanical and Materials Engineering at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University. This award recognizes exceptional Teaching Assistants who have been nominated by their departments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to extend my profound gratitude to my wife Veronica, who has the courage to stand by my side every single day, to everyone in the Department, including my supervisor &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Piomelli&lt;/a&gt; and my fellow colleagues at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/TSMLab.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TSM-Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and to every instructor I have had the pleasure to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I joined How To Change The World program as teaching assistant for the February 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/htctw/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/htctw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 2021 I was selected by Queen&amp;rsquo;s University as part of the Teaching Team for the incredible &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.htctw.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How to Change the World&lt;/a&gt; program. This was my very first experience with HTCTW, an experience I will never forget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.htctw.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HTCTW&lt;/a&gt; is an educational program to be thought as a Learning Journey. Hundreds of studends from everywhere in the world have the chance to work together in Teams to collaboratively tackle the world&amp;rsquo;s most important challenges as defined by the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is well described in the linkedIn &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/company/htctw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;page&lt;/a&gt;, HTCTW has three main aims:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expand the availability and increase the accessibility of our learning journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support universities and colleges to integrate our experiential learning into their curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support the growing community of alumni and partners with implementing real change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say that the pandemic put all of us through a lot of challenges, but it also gave rise to new opportunities. In these 5 days of intense learning experience I have seen students from all over the world, working together in teams, and brainstorming wonderful ideas to tackle the development goals. This has absolutely NO price!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you HTCTW, it was both an honor and a pleasure to be part of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I joined the Turbulence Simulation and Modelling (TSM) Lab</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/tsm_joined/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/tsm_joined/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the TSM Lab, my collegues and I study the fascinating problem of Turbulent Flows. I have always been captured by turbulence. Sometimes I found myself staring at the flames in a fireplace wondering how someone can even try to predict the behavior of flames themselves or the motion of smoke and plumes. Working in this group is a wonderful opportunity to satisfy my deep curiosity. Day by day I am unlocking new physical and mathematical features of turbulent flows that make this problem scary and fascinating at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following years I will investigate the physics of turbulent boundary layers under the effect of strong pressure gradients.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
