<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>University | Dr. Ambrogi</title>
    <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/category/university/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/category/university/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>University</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/media/icon_hu6f17802a8753f91cf448893ebab15783_26243_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>University</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/category/university/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>I received the 2025 Golden Apple Award.</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/gaa_25/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/gaa_25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 6th 2025 I had the pleasure of attending the 2025 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.engsoc.queensu.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Engineering Society&lt;/a&gt; banquet, and I absolutely loved it. I should clarify that this event was entirely organized, planned, and ran by students, and it was WONDERFUL. During the night more than 20 awards were presented to students and faculty members that made a significant impact on the Queen&amp;rsquo;s community. The amount of appreciation and care that students have for one another at this university is truly moving, and something I have never seen anywhere else. It was just beautiful to witness, and this is the reason I LOVE working in this institution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Golden Apple was created in December of 1970 by the Engineering Society Development Committee as a means for undergraduate students to honor faculty members. I was nominated for the Golden Apple award by a student (Ian) who made a speech I will hardly forget. Here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are professors who teach the material—and then there are professors who make students feel truly seen. This one brings a remarkable energy to every lecture, delivering thermodynamics and fluid mechanics concepts with clarity, passion, and a spark that makes learning feel exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They take the time to get to know their students, learning names and checking in—not just academically, but personally. They regularly gather feedback and, more impressively, act on it—always looking for ways to make their courses better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their care extends beyond the classroom. Whether it’s asking how the week is going, attending the Tron hockey game with their family, or hanging out in student spaces, they make it clear that students matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They lead with humility, warmth, and a deep respect for their students—never putting themselves on a pedestal, and always creating a space where students feel comfortable and supported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For their energy in the classroom, their compassion outside of it, their commitment to student growth, and their unwavering dedication to making engineering education better every single day—it is with deep appreciation and admiration that I present the Golden Apple Award to Francesco Ambrogi.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ian&amp;rsquo;s words means everything to me, and they are probably more important than the Award itself. I became a professor today because about 7 years ago another professor made an impact on my academic and learning journey. My biggest dream is to do the same to the new generations of leaders, engineers, and young professionals, and Ian&amp;rsquo;s words made me realize I might just be on the right track!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./GAA_25_2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Jamie, Francesco, Jamie, Ian&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks everyone!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The marvel of shark-skin for fluid mechanics</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/sharkskin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/sharkskin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/a0c0s4K6BTE?si=rB9EK-R9SGDlZ4Zw&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About the speakers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Gianmarco D&#39;Alessandro&lt;/strong&gt;: Gianmarco earned his PhD from Queen&#39;s University where he worked as a graduate research assistant in Prof. Piomelli&#39;s group. Gianmarco then moved to Vietnam where he is a lecturer at RMIT university.
&lt;h2&gt;The marvel of sharks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharks have been around for millions of years, and if there is something that Nature does extremely well, is optimize its creature to thrive in their respective environment. Sharks are no exceptions: they have evolved to be incredible swimmers, fearless predators, and have developed on their skin something known as &lt;em&gt;dermal denticles&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over four decades scientists have tried to explain why shark-skin denticles have evolved to that particular geometry, and the reason might just be &lt;strong&gt;hydrodynamics&lt;/strong&gt;. After a brief introduction, in the video we go over the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drag force in fluid mechanics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shark skin Vs Riblets: differences and similarities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shark skin for viscous drag reduction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shark skin for form drag reduction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shark skin inspired aerospace technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impact of shark skin in aerospace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subscribe to &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtube.com/@ambrogifra-fluids?si=lvt06ca38VYxoyze&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;my YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; and stay tuned for more content like this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joining Queen&#39;s as an assistant professor</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/qu_joined/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/qu_joined/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often tell this story to students in my class: Italy, fall 2017, I was a curious master student following a (very difficult) fluid mechanics class. Confused about the boundary layer thickness I asked a question. The professor paused, erased the board, and explained the same concept in three different ways. That day we did not learn any new concept, and I am sure the professor did not complete his daily plan, but everybody (including a very happy me) walked out of the class with a very clear understanding of boundary layer theory. That day I was inspired, and that professor profoundly changed my future choices. I knew then, I wanted to DO THAT to other students!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of May 1st 2025, I will join the Mechanical and Materials Engineering department at &lt;a href=&#34;https://smithengineering.queensu.ca/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stephen J. R. Smith Faculty of Engineering and Applied Science&lt;/a&gt; at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University as an assistant professor. I have been dreaming about this moment since that fall of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will teach and do research in a beautiful and safe environment among wonderful colleagues: people that I want to learn from, people I can&amp;rsquo;t wait to work with, and people that had a huge impact on my academic career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am beyond excited to be part of reimagining Engineering Education in what will probably be the most exciting years for both students and educators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AD MAIORA SEMPER&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was awarded the 2025 Silver Wrench Award by the MME Department.</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/swa_award_25/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/swa_award_25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a month!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the 3rd consecutive year I received the Silver Wrench Award by the mechanical and materials engineering department at &lt;a href=&#34;https://smithengineering.queensu.ca/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stephen J. R. Smith Faculty of Engineering and Applied Science at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University&lt;/a&gt;. This time was even more special as I co-won the award with my colleague &lt;a href=&#34;https://smithengineering.queensu.ca/directory/faculty/john-w-kurelek.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;John Kurelek&lt;/a&gt;. Note that both of us teach in the thermo-fluids curriculum.
FLUID MECHANICS AT QUEENS ROCKS! 🌊&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other award that filled my heart with joy is the &amp;ldquo;Most approachable professor&amp;rdquo; award by the Mechatronics and Robotics engineering program, that I received during the first ever TRON banquet. This award is presented to the professor who creates a welcoming environment for questions, whether in class or office hours, making sure no student feels like their question is a bad one. Building a safe and welcoming learning environment is at the core of my teaching philosophy, and I could not be happier for this outcome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./MAP_25.png&#34; alt=&#34;MAP award 2025&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks everyone!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was awarded the 2024 Silver Wrench Award by the MME Department.</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/swa_award_24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/swa_award_24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Winter term 2024 I had the pleasure, AGAIN, to teach Fluid Mechanics to second year Queen&amp;rsquo;s Engineering students. It has been, once again, an amazing experience insightful and fullfilling. During the Mechanical Engineering Banquet I received for the second consecutive year the Silver Wrench Award!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented on an annual basis, this award recognizes the professor who displays the most interest and enthusiasm towards Mechanical Engineering as chosen by the graduating year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to extend my profound gratitude to my wife Veronica, who has the courage to stand by my side every single day, to everyone in the Department, including my supervisor &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Piomelli&lt;/a&gt; and my fellow colleagues at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/TSMLab.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TSM-Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and to every instructor I have had the pleasure to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I successfully defended my PhD thesis</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/defense-success/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/defense-success/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a fantastic journey!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 8th, 2023 I successfully defended my PhD thesis titled &amp;ldquo;Characterization of unsteady separation on a turbulent boundary layer&amp;rdquo;. I had a beautiful discussion with the examination committee and gained a lot of useful insights. I now cannot wait to jump into the next step of my academic career! Stay tuned &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These 4 years at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University have been the best of my life. I met incredible people, bright minds, and excited students ready to start their own journey. I had the opportunity to travel to conferences, publish papers, give seminars, and teach core courses in mechanical engineering. It&amp;rsquo;s a path that I strongly suggest to anyone with a deep curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge thank you goes to my supervisor, &lt;a href=&#34;https://smithengineering.queensu.ca/directory/faculty/ugo-piomelli&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Piomelli&lt;/a&gt;, to my colleagues at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://smithengineering.queensu.ca/mme/faculty/piomelli/tsm-lab.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TSM Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and to the wonderful admin &amp;amp; academic staff of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://smithengineering.queensu.ca/mme/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mechanical and Materials Engineering Department&lt;/a&gt; in the Stephen J. R. Smith Faculty of Engineering and Applied Science at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University. You have been part of my journey and I will cherish every single memory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was awarded the 2023 Silver Wrench Award by the MME Department.</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/swa_award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/swa_award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Winter term 2023, I had the wonderful opportunity to teach Fluid Mechanics I (MECH241) to second year engineering students at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University. It was an amazing experience: it was refreshing, stimulating, and exciting. It was my very first time desiging a course from the beginning, and teaching some of the topic I am extremely passionate about. For my work as teaching fellow, I received the Silver Wrench Award on April 2023 during the Mechanical Engineering Banquet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented on an annual basis, this award recognizes the professor who displays the most interest and enthusiasm towards Mechanical Engineering as chosen by the graduating year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to extend my profound gratitude to my wife Veronica, who has the courage to stand by my side every single day, to everyone in the Department, including my supervisor &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Piomelli&lt;/a&gt; and my fellow colleagues at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/TSMLab.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TSM-Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and to every instructor I have had the pleasure to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was awarded the 2022 Bronze Wrench Award by the MME Department.</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/bwa_award/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/bwa_award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented on an annual basis, this award recognizes a teaching assistant of Mechanical Engineering for their contribution to the undergraduate class as voted by all years (2nd , 3rd and 4th ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to extend my profound gratitude to my wife Veronica, who has the courage to stand by my side every single day, to everyone in the Department, including my supervisor &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Piomelli&lt;/a&gt; and my fellow colleagues at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/TSMLab.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TSM-Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and to every instructor I have had the pleasure to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I was awarded the 2022 Dean&#39;s Teaching Assistant Award.</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/dta_award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/dta_award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means EVERYTHING to me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been selected as a recipient of the 2022 Dean&amp;rsquo;s Teaching Assistant (DTA) award by the Department of Mechanical and Materials Engineering at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University. This award recognizes exceptional Teaching Assistants who have been nominated by their departments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to extend my profound gratitude to my wife Veronica, who has the courage to stand by my side every single day, to everyone in the Department, including my supervisor &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Piomelli&lt;/a&gt; and my fellow colleagues at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://me.queensu.ca/People/Piomelli/TSMLab.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TSM-Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and to every instructor I have had the pleasure to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I joined How To Change The World program as teaching assistant for the February 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/htctw/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/htctw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 2021 I was selected by Queen&amp;rsquo;s University as part of the Teaching Team for the incredible &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.htctw.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How to Change the World&lt;/a&gt; program. This was my very first experience with HTCTW, an experience I will never forget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.htctw.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HTCTW&lt;/a&gt; is an educational program to be thought as a Learning Journey. Hundreds of studends from everywhere in the world have the chance to work together in Teams to collaboratively tackle the world&amp;rsquo;s most important challenges as defined by the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is well described in the linkedIn &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/company/htctw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;page&lt;/a&gt;, HTCTW has three main aims:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expand the availability and increase the accessibility of our learning journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support universities and colleges to integrate our experiential learning into their curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support the growing community of alumni and partners with implementing real change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say that the pandemic put all of us through a lot of challenges, but it also gave rise to new opportunities. In these 5 days of intense learning experience I have seen students from all over the world, working together in teams, and brainstorming wonderful ideas to tackle the development goals. This has absolutely NO price!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you HTCTW, it was both an honor and a pleasure to be part of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I joined the Turbulence Simulation and Modelling (TSM) Lab</title>
      <link>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/tsm_joined/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://FrancescoAmbrogi.github.io/post/tsm_joined/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the TSM Lab, my collegues and I study the fascinating problem of Turbulent Flows. I have always been captured by turbulence. Sometimes I found myself staring at the flames in a fireplace wondering how someone can even try to predict the behavior of flames themselves or the motion of smoke and plumes. Working in this group is a wonderful opportunity to satisfy my deep curiosity. Day by day I am unlocking new physical and mathematical features of turbulent flows that make this problem scary and fascinating at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following years I will investigate the physics of turbulent boundary layers under the effect of strong pressure gradients.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
